#大家好 很多粉絲跟我們說 這個竹鼠
Hi everyone! Many fans ask us what will happen,
#竹鼠跟那個老鼠啊 放在一起會怎麼樣
if a bamboo, a bamboo rat is placed together with a mouse.
#我們也不知道哦
We have no ideas.
#我們上山上摘點那個 (註︰用"get"是因為與"catch"發音相近，又有「摘」的意思)
So let's go onto the hill and get some,
#我們上山上抓點這個 老鼠下來
let's go onto the hill and catch some mice.
#給我們家的竹鼠玩一下
So that our bamboo rats can have some fun with them.
#看一下會怎麼樣
Let's what will happen.
#這個是老鼠籠
This is a mouse trap.
#買的哦
I bought them.
#我們去挖點攝影小哥家的番薯
Let's dig some sweet potatoes from Mr. Cameraman's place.
#番薯給它做誘餌
which are to be used as bait.
#沒有番薯
Without the sweet potatoes,
#那個老鼠它是不會進去的哦
the mice will never go into the traps.
#可以
Alright!
#先去挖點番薯來
Get some sweet potatoes first.
#終於到了攝影小哥家的那個
Finally we arrived at the sweet potatoes field,
#紅薯地
at Mr. Cameraman's place.
#那麼遠
So far away!
#還要我跑那麼遠過來
Why should I come all the way here?
#割都不用割了
I don't wanna cut.
#用拔
Just pull!
#用手拔就行啦
Pull with my hands!
#這個苗 又可以帶回去給小豬吃了
The leaves, we can bring them back for the piggies.
#小豬很喜歡吃的哦
The piggies love the leaves so much.
#今天就把這三行
I'll have these three rows today.
#把它拱掉就好啦 (註︰「拱」應該是指無差別的破壞吧)
Simply loot everything.
#你看
Look!
#這都把它捆好啦
Let me tie them up.
#鋤頭帶的太小了
The pickaxe is too small.
#帶這個鋤頭
This pickaxe is...
#你看 這個小番薯啊
Look! This small sweat potato,
#很好吃的哦
tastes really good.
#這很小的
This is very small.
#好深啊
So deep.
#你看
Look!
#你看 挖番薯挖了個四腳蛇
Look! Coming with the sweat potatoes, is a gecko!
#這四腳蛇很靚的
The gecko is so beautiful.
#它們現在冬眠了 鑽到那洞裡面去 (註︰他指的洞應該是指泥裏的洞而已)
The geckos are now hibernating, inside the soil.
#這個四腳蛇它會咬人的哦 要小心哦
I need to be careful, as the gecko bites.
#不過我們
But we,
#我們
we,
#習慣了就沒事了
we've already got used to it.
#它爪子 好利呀
The claws, are very sharp.
#等下我把它放了
I'm releasing it now.
#四腳蛇 遇到我算你運氣好
Gecko. You're lucky that I am the one you meet today.
#有點像恐龍哦 它這四腳蛇
It looks a bit like a dinosaur, the gecko.
#是把 你看
Right? Look!
#被我逮到了 不然放了 它要咬我 它一直想 想咬我 (註︰這句基本上是上文不接下理的)
I got it. Otherwise, if it's released... It wants to bite me, it always wants, wants to bite me.
#我把它放了
I release it now.
#快 走啦
Alright, go!
#挖了那麼一點點
We got just a bit here.
#夠了
It's enough!
#最少三十斤啊 這個
At least 15 kg, here.
#挖紅薯挖的太過癮啦
Digging sweat potatoes is too much fun.
#天都黑啦
It's getting dark now.
#我們明天再去放那個龍子
We'll place the traps tomorrow.
#現在
Now,
#現在準備把那個
we're giving all these,
#餵豬
to the pigs.
#這個是拿出
This will be taken,
#拿出去攝影小哥家餵那個兔子的
taken by Mr. Cameraman's back home for the rabbits.
#這個紅薯葉
These are the leaves.
#去搞一點紅薯出來啊
Let's get some sweat potatoes,
#給家人吃
for our families.
#第二天 (註︰共有四天)
Day 2
#我們準備去後山放那個籠子
We're setting off onto the hill to place the traps.
#你看 這是紅薯
Look! These are the sweat potatoes.
#這裡都是
There are,
#長滿了綠葉草哦
green grass everywhere.
#長滿了野花
flowers everywhere.
#你看 這個是紅薯哦
Look! This is a sweat potato.
#把它當成誘餌
Place it here as a bait,
#來誘那個老鼠
to attract the mice.
#你看 這樣就可以了
This is good enough.
#老鼠一拉 一拉這個紅薯 它就嘣的一聲掉下去
When the mouse pulls, pulls the sweat potato, then "Bang!", the gate is shut.
#我們示範一下哦
Let's show you.
#我這樣戳一下
I shake it.
#肯定跑不了 鑽進去了就
There's no escape, once it gets in.
#放在這裡面
Put it inside.
#放在這裡正好
It's perfect here.
#搞點樹枝蓋一下
Cover it with leaves and branches,
#偽裝一下
to disguise it.
#好啦 放好一個啦
Alright! This one is done.
#我再放另外一個
Let's move on to the next one.
#放下面
Down there,
#好像有老鼠咬過哦
seems to have been bitten by mice.
#這裡又可以放一個
A trap can be placed here,
#搞個紅薯
with a sweat potato.
#放在這裡
Put it here.
#你看
Look!
#這樣就可以啦
A trap is set.
#等下老鼠一進去就
Once a mouse gets it,
#一咬那個紅薯就啪的一聲掉下來
once it bites the sweat potato, then "Pa!", the gate is shut.
#我們再去其它地方放
Let's place a few more at other places.
#這裡有一條路 你看
Here's a path, look!
#從這走下來 然後到這裡喝水
They come all the way down, and have a drink here.
#這裡也放一個
So, put a trap here.
#放在這裡
Put it here.
#然後它自己會進去
The mice will then get in by themselves.
#這裡有一個東西吃
Here is food.
#看 放在這裡
Look! Put it here.
#好 這樣又一個
Good! So one more.
#還有個放這裡
And the last one here.
#這樣就可以了
It should be alright.
#老鼠一下來
When the mice come down.
#這個要一晚上 晚上它才出來活動的 這個老鼠
It takes a night. The mice are coming out only at night.
#現在我們回去了
Let's go back home now.
#這藤條擋我路
This branch is blocking my way.
#哇 山上的水坑裡面有一條蛇哦
Wa! There's a snake in the pit on the hill.
#你看 掉水坑了
Look! It fell into the pit.
#這個又不是水蛇 這個是我們這邊
It's not a water snake. It's called,
#我們這邊叫那個 水律蛇
it's called oriental ratsnake here.
#就是 yong蛇 我們土話叫yong蛇
In fact it's "yong" snake, it's called "yong" snake in our local dialect.
#學名叫水律蛇 (註︰這也不是學名吧，不過似乎這是一個較正式的名，所以英文亦用了一個感覺較高尚的)
Formally it's called "oriental ratsnake".
#誒呦 它想咬我 你看
Ayo! It wants to bite me, look!
#太壞了你
Bad guy!
#它應該從這樹上掉下來的
It should have fallen from the tree.
#它這個蛇不 這個蛇不會下水的
This snake doesn't, this snake never gets into the water.
#肯定是不小心掉下去
It must be an accident.
#我把它撈起來
Let me get it our from the water.
#它還不願意起來一樣哦
It doesn't seem to be very willing.
#你會死掉的 在這下面
You can't survive inside the pit.
#下不去了
I can't make it.
#你看 是不是
Look! Right?
請勿摸仿
DO NOT IMITATE!
#你看 好大條啊 看一下
Look! It's huge! Have a look!
#算啦 把它放生算啦
Okay! I'd better release it.
#這麼小
It's so small.
#你看 它想咬我
Look! It wants to bite me!
#大家不要模仿 不要模仿我去抓蛇哦
It's not an example to you. Never, never catch a snake!
#就是 有些蛇是有毒的哦 千萬不要碰
You know, some snakes are venomous. Don't even touch them!
#咬到的話 後果很嚴重的哦
Things can get be deadly if you got bitten.
#好啦
Alright!
#我要回去啦
It's time to go back now.
#把那條蛇放生啦
The snake is released.
#第三天
Day 3
#今天我們來收一下這個老鼠竉
Today we're going to get back the mouse traps.
#看到這兩個 老鼠今天 肯定昨天晚上沒來
Look at these two traps. Certainly, certainly the mice today, have not come last night.
#都沒 沒有裝到
No, couldn't catch any.
#我們去看一下其他地方
Let's have a look at other places.
#我看了一遍
I've checked all traps once.
#一個老鼠都沒有
There's not even a single mouse.
#還沒進去裡面吃
They've not got into the traps.
#我們明天再過來看一下
Let's come again tomorrow.
#第四天
Day 4
#你看
Look!
#狗在叫哦
The dogs are barking!
#上面應該有
There must be a mouse,
#有一隻老鼠
a mouse up there.
#這個籠子都沒抓到
The trap here couldn't catch any.
#看山上
Let's go up.
#你看 抓了一個小老鼠哦
Look! A small mouse is caught.
#好靈活啊它
It's very agile.
#是不是吃飽了
You've had a good meal?
#那麼小的 這就是
So small. It's in fact,
#這就是我們家的山老鼠
in fact it's a wild mouse here.
#白肚皮的
The belly is white,
#毛有點黃的
and the hair is a bit brown.
#我把它拿回去
Let me take it back.
#我它把拿回去
Let me take it back,
#給我家的竹鼠玩一下
and let my bamboo rats play with it.
#好靈活 你看 小老鼠
So agile! Look! Little mouse.
#我們提回去
Let's take it back.
#我把這個老鼠放到竹鼠池裡面去
I'm now putting the mouse into the bamboo rat cell.
#來
Come on!
#給你加餐
Your extra meal!
#它在咬籠子
It's biting the cage.
#它想把籠子咬開
It wants to break the cage,
#然後再吃那個老鼠吧
and eat the mouse.
#小老鼠好厲害呦 你看
The little mouse is not to be sniffed at, look!
#竹鼠都不敢動它
The bamboo rat doesn't even dare to touch it.
#我們換一個兇一點的來
Let's switch to a more fierce one.
#這個不夠兇
This is not fierce enough.
#你看
Look!
#把這個小老鼠放下去
Let me put the little mouse into the cell,
#給他們玩
for them to play.
#下去
Get down!
#竟然不想下
Why doesn't it want to?
#不想下的話就很麻煩了哦
It would be difficult if it doesn't want to.
#吃貨
Foodaholic!
#哎呀 想跳出來
Aya! It wants to get out.
#看這個竹鼠 竹鼠好像慫了
Look at the bamboo rat. It looks scared.
#你看這個老鼠 這老鼠太小了 竹鼠都對它沒興趣
Look at the mouse. The mouse is too small. It can't attract the interest of the bamboo rat.
#大幾倍耶
It's several times larger.
#去咬它 去
Bite it! Come on!
#咬它
Bite it!
#不咬它
Why don't you bite?
#怎麼那麼老實了
When did you become so nice and gentle?
#快點來 咬它 這裡有好吃的
Hurry up! Bite it! Here's something tasty!
#去
Just go!
#嘿呦 快點去咬它
Heyo! Come on, bite it!
#怎麼不去咬它 去咬它啊
Why don't you bite it? Bite it!
#不咬
Why not?
#去 咬它
Come on! Bite it!
#這不咬它
You're not biting at all!
#跑啦 跑啦
Damn it! It runs away!
#剛剛 抓的那老鼠太小了 從這縫裡面跑了
The mouse is too small so it has just run away through the gap.
#現在都不知道路哪裡去了
I don't know where it is now.
#不管它了
I don't care.
#好啦 把這個竹鼠
Alright! This bamboo rat,
#放回這裡
I put it here.
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡了
Alright! The video ends here.
#下次我們抓一個大的來
Next time we'll catch a large mouse,
#再給它們玩
to let them play.
#它們都沒玩
They haven't had enough fun.